Good morning.
Good morning. Good
afternoon. Good
evening, depending
on when you see this.
Welcome to the first
of my, I believe, five
pulmonary lectures.
My name is Jason
Goldman. I am a proud
NYT comm graduate from,
I don't want to tell
you what, year 2000.
And it's my great honor to
share pulmonary with you.
Today we're going to do PE
and then there's a break,
and then I have a bunch
of lectures, I don't know,
about two months away. So
I'm super, super excited.
Today, we're going to
talk about thromboembolic
disease, which is the
grand total of deep vein
thrombosis and pulmonary
embolism together, DVT and PE.
I'm obsessed as the
pulmonary guy with looking
for and diagnosing and
appropriately managing DVT
and PE can be fatal, and
we'll talk about that.
It's an exciting time in
healthcare. Things
are consistently
evolving, and I think
you're going to have an
amazing experience through
the rest of your second
year, and then I look
forward to seeing you out
in your third and fourth
years. I am the Chief
Medical Officer for
Catholic Health, which
includes Good Samaritan,
St. Francis, St. Joseph's,
St. Catherine's,
Mercy, and St. Charles,
so we have residents
flowing through many of
those hospitals, of
which hopefully there'll
be a lot of NICOM
or NYTCOM graduates.
And I'm a pulmonary
critical care doc, still
seeing patients in
the pulmonary office.
So let's get started.
Here's just some objectives.
Now, in my lectures,
what I'm going to try
to do is highlight
what's really important,
as well as a lot of true
clinical pearls, things
that you take to your
third year, right? We're
not learning this in a
vacuum. The whole point
is to manage patients.
And you'll hear me say
a number of times over
the course of my lectures,
the most important
thing that you need to
learn as a medical student
is who's sick and who's
not sick. Now, keep
that in perspective. Anybody
who's seeing a doctor
traditionally, if
there's a complaint, they
have some sort of illness
or sickness going on.
But that's not what I'm
talking about. You need to
look at somebody and
say, who's potentially
critically ill? Who could
decompensate? Who could die?
And those people
demand your urgent
attention. So a lot of
what we do is a mental
triage, and we'll
talk about that as we
go. All right, so DVT
and PE, what is it?
Predisposing factors,
what's DVT, what's PE?
How do we diagnose?
How do we prevent? How
do we treat with
anticoagulants? Sometimes
you need to clock bust
them with thrombolytics
and, you know, other
treatment approaches.
So again, the total
thromboembolic disease includes
DVT and PE. Now,
traditionally, DVTs are in the
legs, but you can have DVTs
in the arms. You can have
them a lot of places. And
you could have traditional
pulmonary embolized,
which are little clots
that break off from the
deep vein thrombosis in the
leg and shoot off. And
what they do is they go up
the inferior vein of cava
into the right side of the
heart, right atrium,
right ventricle, and then
out into the pulmonary
artery. And they get caught
in the pulmonary circulation
because it's so small.
And as they block flow,
it's simple plumbing.
It's simple plumbing. If you
block the flow, what you're
going to get is you're
going to get a backup behind
it, right? It's as if your
toilet is clogged, and it's
going to start to cause
ramifications on your body.
It can lead to
right heart failure,
which can lead to
death, ultimately.
Deep vein thrombosis can cause
the same effect
locally as well.
You can also embolize
not just clots. You can
embolize cement, and you
can embolize amniotic
fluid. A lot of things
can embolize through the
body. But traditionally,
we refer to clots that
form for whatever clinical
reason that then break
off, go to the right side
of the heart, and cause
some clinical impact of
a pulmonary embolism.
That's a picture of some
clot. You can actually go
in. This was taken out
via open heart, but you
can now extract with cool
interventional devices,
pull out that clot, and
look at that clot burden.
Imagine that sitting in
your pulmonary vasculature.
And it's a real disease.
This is a famous story.
This was back in the early,
one of the Gulf Wars.
This reporter was
embedded with our troops.
I was sitting in one
of those, you know,
armored personnel carriers.
And it was kind of
scrunched up for a bunch of
hours and had developed
some swelling in his leg.
Or, you know, as the story
goes and shared it with
the doctors and deployed or
the medics. And they said,
you know, we're concerned.
You have a clot. You need
to stand down. and he
didn't. He said, no, no, I
want to keep going. I didn't
seek treatment, and there
was a DVT, and it did
embolize, and it killed him.
Really, really sad story.
Lots of other people have
died from clots. You'd
be amazed or have had
clots. Heavy D, the rapper,
died of a pulmonary embolism.
Serena Williams has had a
well-publicized, you know,
I mean, the best, one of
the best tennis players
ever right um had uh
pulmonary embolism has had
anticoagulation issues we
when you get a clot we thin
your blood we anticoagulate
you so that clot
doesn't embolize uh and
then that itself can cause
complications uh regis
philbin you guys may be too
young but he was he was the
good morning america you
know alive at regis guy
for many many many years
and he had a
pulmonary embolism.
Al Roker recently, look at
this, this is his quote.
This is about a
year or two ago,
which look how he describes
it. Last week I was admitted
to the hospital with a
blood clot of my light DVT,
which sent some
clots to my lung.
Really, really, the
disease is out there.
We feel that this is
a critical diagnosis,
something that
will never go away.
Lots of reviews. this is
some kind of recent reviews
in JAMA or New England
Journal. They're out there.
They make for great reads.
The treatment paradigm and
even the diagnostic paradigm
is consistently evolving.
It's still the same concept,
but it only evolves like
anything else in healthcare.
But these are nice if you
want something to read.
So DVT is a blood platform
within a deep vein
of the leg there are
superficial veins and deep
veins it's a superficial
venous thrombus is that
if it's in a superficial
vein but most of the
veins that we're discussing
here are deep veins
and then a pulmonary
embolism like we discussed
something breaks off clot
I wrote substance because
again there can be other
things but traditionally it's
a clot from somewhere in
the body you can have it
from the arm as well but
it's usually traditionally
lower extremity DVT leads
to pulmonary embolism.
Here's some epidemiology
between, let
me see if I can
move this bar here.
Oh yeah, that's good.
Between 100,000, 300
,000 deaths every year,
right? It's a big
deal. And it used to,
it's still a huge
deal, but we didn't
have as good a hand
of it in the hospital.
U.S. Surgeon General for
years ago, this is one of the
most common preventable
cause of death among
hospitalized patients um I believe
that I'm absolutely obsessed
um uh um that our patients
should all be appropriately
prophylaxed whatever
it means for them uh to
prevent a clot uh when they're
in the hospital and I I
take it as a personal um
front if you know if I see a
patient and they don't have
dbt prophylaxis on board
uh let's see here um here's
a cool picture of what's
called a saddle pulmonary
embolism saddle because
it's it's across both sides
you can see here's the
pulmonary artery it goes
from the right side to the
left side I can see if you
can see my arrow but this
is obviously post-mortem
you don't want this because
think about it remember
I explained it's simple
plumbing if you have clot
taking up the whole pulmonary
artery up into the right
and left sides, both upper
and lower lungs, there's
not going to be any blood
flow. And without blood
flow, obviously, you die.
And this is a post-mortem
picture of that. There
is a way to treat this
if a patient has this.
Obviously, you can go in,
extract the clot, you can give
clot busters, and we'll
talk about that later on.
Most cases of pulmonary
embolism are not this
extensive saddle pulmonary
embolism, but it happens.
Predisposing factors, so
here's your physiology,
it's usually Virchow's
triad, which I expect you
know, hypercoagulation,
vascular damage, and
venous stasis leads to
this. Let's talk about
hypercoagulation. So you
could have inherited or
acquired abnormalities of
the coagulation system. And
we'll talk about some
of those causes of both.
You add that in with some
vascular damage, whether
it's post-surgical, you
bang your leg, whatever it
happens to be, and it
activates tissue factors and
has coagulation in the
area. And then you add
that with circulatory
stasis, which we see
from, again, the
plumbing backing up.
And therefore, it's
constantly irritating
that area. When you
put this together,
this Virchus triad,
you get thrombosis,
DVT, and ultimately peeve.
Clinical risk factors.
So here's some of the
big ones. Put a little
star on this slide.
inside immobility, whether
it's post-surgical,
you know, feeling
good. We see patients,
sometimes elderly patients
that have gotten, you
know, whatever, bad
flu, and they're staying
on the couch for a
few days. They didn't
get off the couch. When
you get the history,
and then they come in,
there's a swollen leg on top
of their, you know, non
-resolving pneumonia, flu, what
have you, and you got to
be suspicious. You got to
look for it. I always, always,
always, always, always,
and you'll hear me say this
all day, think of pulmonary
embolism. History of
previous on bone biotic
disease, probably the top
risk factor. Use of estrogen,
we'll talk about that
pregnancy, cancer, CHF, because
of slow flow through the
body, deficiency of inherited
factors that prevent
coagulation or acquired factors.
So let's, again, so
star that slide, this is
an important one.
Likely you can imagine a
question would come
from the risk factors,
because if you don't
know to look for the
risk factors, you won't
think of the disease.
Immobility, top of
the list is post
-surgical, right?
Especially big belly,
abdominal, joint
surgery, huge risk.
Our orthopedic surgeons
are very, very well
-versed in DVT prophylaxis.
Trauma, you can
imagine somebody in a multi
-vehicle trauma getting
laid up and that becomes
a nidus for clots,
cancer. So cancer leads
to increased venous stasis
essentially through the
body. It's a high clotting
environment in the body,
high risk of clotting, and
therefore anybody with cancer
who has anything that's
something potentially for
PE, I'm thinking of PE, DVT,
heart disease with acute
MI and THF, that's really
for low flow states and
obesity. Some really
interesting literature on
obesity, the unknown etiology.
History of previous, this
is the top of the list. So
when I hear the patient had a
clot was on anticoagulation,
whether it's even after
post-surgical clot or
it's an unknown clot, I'm
saying my long bones are going,
oh, really? Tell me about
that. And I want to know
more about that. Estrogen.
So we see this with oral
contraceptive use. It's not
the progesterone dosing.
It's the estrogen dosing. And
it's really the combination
of estrogen and oral
contraceptives plus smokers.
When you add that
smoking in, that's a
vicious combination
and it goes up to, you
know, six plus times
higher than a baseline.
We can see the estrogen
in their fertility
and there's an adjunct
in treatment of
malignancy, postmenopausal
estrogen replacement.
And so you have to think
about that when you hear that.
The whole point of what we
do in medicine is we take,
we meet a patient, we have
this huge kind of area of
questions. And we ask
questions and we look at their
medications and we look at
their history and it helps us
narrow until we have a good
differential diagnosis of
what could be going on.
And then we whittle through
that to try to prove or
disprove what the diagnosis is.
Pregnancy, really
see this in late
stages of postpartum.
We've all heard
about post-pregnancy
or peripregnancy.
Clots, seven times greater
than and non-pregnant.
But here's a really
great fact. So this is
an important start.
There's two-thirds of this
occur in the immediate
postpartum period.
So low extremity and
pelvic venous stasis.
There's some dilation,
thrombocytosis. And look at
this quote on the bottom,
incidence of fatal PE after
CESAR is nine times greater.
I'm not going to ask
you about the nine times,
but you need to be thinking
about this, that clots
occur in the immediate
postpartum and the fatal PEs
after C-section is greater
than vaginal. So C-section
is surgery. So think about
that. So you're pregnant,
you have an increased
risk, and then you have a
C-section. So you have an
abdominal surgery. And
pregnancy really cranks up the
risk. So that's how we're
thinking of these things.
You can see that non
-pregnancy associated
DVT, maybe low to flat,
but pregnancy associated
one keeps going.
This is data from 20
years ago, but still
applicable, the concept.
cancer trousseau described
this more than 100 years ago
especially with lung pancreas
breast gigu has to do
with the procoagulant material
floating around the body
sometimes sometimes you'll
see you know whatever a 50
year old guy who comes in
with a uh occult dbt or pe
and you certainly need
to be suspicious why did
they get the clot if
they have no risk factors
they didn't have surgery
they're not I always always
go hunting for underlying
cancer right So you
do the basic screening
stuff, look for prostate,
look for colon. I mean,
screen, scan the body.
And of course, if you
see trousseau's sign of
malignancy, it's a
migratory thrombophobitis.
And I'm certainly,
you likely know that.
Inheritive risk
factors, are there any
kind of clotting
deficiency, antithrombin
3 deficiency,
protein C, protein S,
factor 5, Leiden,
and G202 when you
don't want O mutation?
So part of the work
of a clot is to use
these, to look at
these levels, work in
combination with a
hematologist, and try to
determine if there's an
inherited risk factor.
I will point out, put a
star here, factor V Leiden
is the most common
cause, most common cause.
So this is the top of my
list always. If you get a
clinical story and they say
a patient has an inherited
risk factor, which is the
most likely inherited risk
factor they have, it's
factor V Leiden deficiency.
We're seeing a lot of
G202, 1 and 1OA mutations
as well. But it's a
little star. Factor 5
light and most common
cause of inherited
thrombinophlebitis. Very
inherited DBTs and clots.
All right, let's
talk about DBT.
Most clots are silent and
produce no symptoms. So our
body's always clotting and
breaking up the clot in
our body. But sometimes when
something goes askew, one
of those risk factors or
the clotting factors, that
clot then grows and stays.
Sometimes you can just have
it in a calf. So they often
go away in some extent.
And that's where
it gets dangerous
in the more the
proximal deep veins.
Most symptomatic PEs and
virtually all fatal PEs
come from the deep
veins of the legs. Okay,
the proximal deep veins
of the legs. Think about
it because the veins are
big. They're close to
the heart. They can grow.
They can travel fast.
And they can really
cause damage.
Look at this fact. 50% of
patients with symptomatic
proximal vein DBT have a
silent pulmonary embolism.
So when I'm working and
I see a patient that
comes in with a DBT, I'm
going to scan their chest
to see if they have a
silent pulmonary embolism,
you know, if they're
asymptomatic. Now, not
everybody does this. I can't
see the evidence behind
it. But based on this
fact, I'm going to do it.
I'll tell you why. Here's
the logic that I believe.
If you have a clot, you're
going to anticoagulate them.
That's what we do. We'll
talk about it at the end.
what if then two weeks
later they come back showing
us a breath a week later
we've seen this all the
time now you scan them because
they're short of breath
and they have a recent
dbt say oh my *** maybe
they have a pe now you scan
them and you didn't scan
them the first time now
they have a clot so does
that mean they failed that
anticoagulation and were
able to you know have a clot
traverse or was it there
always uh and so I try
to take that question off
the table but I can't say
that's evidence-based let's
talk about dbts most are
so asymptomatic but if
you have it there, nonspecific.
Swelling, tenderness,
redness, edema, right?
So classically, you know,
you think you're cellulitis,
you think you're clot.
Swelling, it's erythematous,
it's warm, it's edematous.
Holman's sign,
that's a positive.
Tenderness, when
you squeeze the
calf on dorsiflexion
of the foot,
we do it. It's very
nonspecific. So everybody says,
oh, what's the Holman's sign?
You need to know it um uh
it would be indicative if
it was you know pain uh you
know when you squeeze the
calf as your dorsiflex the
foot for homenside and say
oh my *** maybe there's a
clot but it's very very
non-specific um it could be
other things as well um uh
70 look at this cool fact 70
of ambulatory patients who
you think may have a clot
have something else but
that's okay 30 that have that
clot so you gotta go looking
for it I'm obsessed with
not missing things um I'm
obsessed with not missing
things uh here's an extreme
example of this patient on
extreme clot with a big
backup of flow and they got a
thermitis a demitis uh you
can see the picture uh here's
an interesting to put a
little start with this one
this is may turner syndrome
uh this is one of those um
zebras you need to know now
here if you have the right
iliac artery crossing the
left iliac vein you can see
it in the picture it's
squishing the vein there um
and that squishing will lead
to venous stasis and you
know the flow slows down
and you get clot um and it's
it's very hard to look for this
and it's hard to understand
the etiology but um when
you find a few of these
you certainly are glad
that you identified this
because then you can
send them to the vascular
surgeon to have some sort
of therapeutic treatment.
What happens to those
clots that form in the leg?
There's fibrinolysis.
They can organize.
So sometimes they go away.
Sometimes they organize
and, you know, can cause
some post-fluidic syndrome.
Sometimes it's bad. I'll
show you a picture of
that. They become chronic
and they just sit there.
And of course, the biggest
issue is embolization.
And interestingly,
the risk is greatest
when the clot is friable,
just like coronary
plaque, right? It's the
soft plaque in the coronary
vessels that thrombolizes,
that thrombosis,
that embolizes and,
you know, causes an MI.
Same thing here. Once
the clot organizes, it's
less likely to travel.
Same thing in the plaque,
right? That's hard plaque
versus soft plaque.
Here's post-pulbetic
syndrome, an extreme example.
You lose your veins.
You lose your valves.
Everything backs up. It
starts to roll out the skin,
and that's an extreme
example. You would go into
wound care, hyperbaric care,
and see if you can treat
the underlying cause
through a vascular surgery.
Let's talk about pulmonary
embolism because this
is where we go. Now,
remember this slide? I
see people that were my
students 10 years ago.
They say, oh, my ***, I
always take a PE, Jay.
Yes, you do. You have to,
right? You never want to
miss pulmonary embolism
because it can be fatal.
It can be one of those
sudden, fatal things we
think about, right? If
you remember, it's one of
the causes in the CPR
algorithm of PEA. So I always,
always, always think
of pulmonary embolism.
What happens is when the
clot breaks off, it goes
into the pulmonary, it
goes up the right side
into the pulmonary arteries,
and it starts to cause
backflow. It affects the
pulmonary circulation
and then causes, you know,
right heart collapse.
The decreased flow
will cause left heart
collapse, and then
the patient dies.
And the degree of impact
it has on the body
traditionally is how big and
where is the clot. If it's
a huge clot burden, you
know, it's like a huge,
you know, obstructing
kidney stone. You know, it
can cause a huge amount
of trouble immediately.
If it's a small
amount of clot, then,
you know, blood
can go around it.
And then the other obvious
thing is what's your
base status? If you are
an end-stage COPD or an
end-stage heart failure
patient, you're going to
have less reserve to
manage even a small clot.
Both of those make sense.
How does a PE present?
Here's the problem. Non
-specific. You've got
to think about it, right?
You've got to be there
for them. So 50% of the
patients who you think
might have a PE have a
PE. So it's a thumbnail.
Oh, that guy may have
a PE. Well, I don't
know, 50-50. But at least
you thought about it.
Presentation is usually
subtle. I always look, if
I find a PE, I'm looking
for a DVT as well.
Similar to when I find a
DVT, I'm looking for a PE.
We talked about what causes
the clinical picture,
and, you know, it may
cause up to 10% of hospital
deaths. I don't think it's
as much anymore because
we're so, I think, I
believe we've gotten so good
about prophylaxis in patients,
but it still happens.
Patients present
traditionally with
shortness of breath.
Doctors can't breathe.
Chest pain, it's usually
pleuritic. Sometimes they
say, it hurts so much when
I take a deep breath. right
here and they point at a
spot you know that one's
kind of simple doesn't
always work like that anxiety
uh there's a sense of doom
uh we've had many stories
of patients say doc I feel
like I'm gonna die and
then they die it's really
when a patient tells you
I feel like I'm gonna die
you pay attention to them
um we didn't see this 10
years ago we've seen more
and more syncope mere
syncope uh so what happens is
the clock goes in and it
starts to decrease the forward
flow left side of the
heart doesn't see as much
flow and the brain starts
to get, you know, low flow
and you syncopize or you
neosyncopize. And normally
then you're thinking of
a cardiac reason or a
neurologic reason, but you
got to think about PE as well.
For this reason, I'm seeing
more and more of this.
Cough and cough,
rare, you know, some cases
where there's even like
burping, you know, of the
clot to touching the nerve,
the phrenic nerve, or
irritating the phrenic nerve.
Hemoptysis, when
somebody's coughing
in blood, obviously
you pay attention.
Most likely cause of
coughing in blood is
bronchitis, but certainly
you got to think
about PE, lung cancer,
a lot of things in
that differential
diagnosis, tuberculosis.
Vitals, they're often
usually tachypneic,
so short breath and
they're breathing
fast. You've got to
count the breaths.
In hospitals, traditionally,
when vitals are
done, they write 20
for the respiratory
rate. Nobody's respiratory
rate at rest is 20.
Check yours is
probably 12 to 14.
So 20 is abnormal to me.
I always check respiratory
rate myself. I just sit
there. You can do it while
you're talking to the
patients. You put your little
timer on, count 30
seconds, and see how many
times that. But if they're
breathing fast, if they're
breathing 25, 30 times a
minute, that's abnormal.
Tachycardia comes and
goes. It's not always
there. It can have fever,
low-grade. It can fool
you. Oh, my ***, are we
septic? But sometimes
PEs can cause low-grade
fever. Focal crackles,
less likely. We're using
a cyanosis, so rare.
Somebody comes in,
chest pain, shortness of
breath, you're going to
get an EKG because I always
think about cardiac,
cardiac, cardiac as well.
Non-specific, non-specific.
So if I ask you most
common finding, put a
little star in this slide,
most common finding of
EKG. Oh, put a star in
this slide, too. You
need to know, obviously,
the symptoms of pulmonary
embolism. I think
that's very important.
But on this slide, most
common finding is nonspecific
STT changes. So I
can certainly imagine
getting that question on
a test. The most specific
finding, pathognomonic
finding of a pleaeon in EKG
is S1Q3T3. I think I have
a picture of it here.
An S in lead one,
a deep Q in lead
three, and a flip
T in lead three.
S1Q3T3. You won't see
this unless you go
looking for it. You've
got to go looking for it.
I found a number of
them over the years,
but only because I
have a high suspicion
to go looking. Let me
see. There's one I've
asked, you know, and
then you look like,
my ***, look how
smart that guy is. But
not really. You're
just looking for it.
EKG really helps you rule
out other stuff, STEMI and,
you know, ischemia, looking
for that stuff. But I'm a
pericarditis, but I'm always
looking for S1, Q3, Q3,
and you can have a right axis
deviation. Think about it
because it's a strain on
the right side of the heart.
pulmonary infarct so you
can if you block some of the
major flow to the pulmonary
vasculature you can infarct
the tissue beyond uh when
you get it it's bad it's
uncommon because of the dual
circulation or the uh to
the to the to the lungs uh
and most common when you have
an under underline disease
uh here's some post-mortem
pictures uh of a patient
with pulmonary infarct what
happens those clots, same
thing that happens in the
legs. Sometimes they fragment.
Sometimes they go away. You
know, they dissolve and go
away. And sometimes they
organize. And you can
get what's called chronic
thromboembolic disease or chronic,
and then which can lead to
chronic thromboembolic
pulmonary hypertension, CTPH.
But similar to the legs.
And always, always, always,
always, always, always,
always think of a PE.
Because if you find
that you can save
a life, you can
literally save a life.
When I think of DBT,
when I think of PE, to
me, it's one disease.
It's one continuous
disease. And I feel
that I'm not doing the
right job if I don't
go looking for both.
Wells criteria. Wells
criteria are scoring criteria.
You don't need to
memorize Wells criteria,
okay? You do not need to
memorize these criteria.
But it's a scoring criteria.
What you want to have
is a pretest probability.
So you see a patient,
you know, again, there's
this many things that can
happen. You need to narrow
it down. This is one way. if
I'm thinking about DVT,
I'm going to apply Wells
criteria. And this is a
scoring system that says, you
know, do they have any, do
they have clinical symptoms
with DVT? Well, yes. And they
get three points. Do they
have another diagnosis
that's less likely than PE?
Then they will get three
points. Like, I doubt it's
MI because the EKG is
normal. And I doubt it's
this. I doubt it's pneumonia
because the chest x
-ray is clear. So all these
things are pointing more
towards PE. Are they
tachycardia, you get points.
Are they recent immobilization
of surgery, you get
points. Do they have a
previous DVT, that's a big
one, you get points. Are
you coughing up blood, and
do you have underlying
cancer? And then based on how
many things are positive,
it helps your pre-test
probability of what's my
diagnostic test of choice.
How am I going to figure
out what this patient has?
All right, so big star in
this slide, huge, huge star.
I'm going to teach you two
different concepts. One
is the gold standard, and
one is the test of choice.
The gold standard may
be the best test in the
whole world. There may
be one that has side
effects. It may be one
that's very expensive. It
may be one that's not
every hospital offers.
So you need to know the
diagnosis. You
need to know both.
So star in this, I'll probably
ask you the difference.
Phenography is the gold
standard. Meaning if I had
my choice and it didn't
have any side effects, this
would be the test. You
would inject the veins with
dye and you'd see if there's
a clot. Pretty simple.
The problem is it's a big
deal. We almost never do
it. almost uh it's invasive
and uh it costs money
and you can have side
effects anytime you do an
invasive whereas you could
just do a lower extremity
doppler venous ultrasound
in the legs so simple
you take the ultrasound
probe you can almost do it
yourself but actually
by the time you guys get
out you probably have an
ultrasound you pop them and
you do it yourself now
you compress and see if
there's a clot in there you
look with the ultrasound
it's highly accurate 95
% sensitive and specific,
it's a great test. So
I'll give you a clinical
scenario. If somebody comes
in and they have a science
and synthesis of DVT,
what's the test of choice?
The answer is venous
ultrasound, lower extremity
Doppler, same thing.
Not venography, right?
You see what the gold
standard was? If I had
unlimited budget and I'm
at this uber academic
hospital, great. But the
test of choice is lower
extremity Doppler, okay?
Which is again, the same
thing as a lower extremity
venous ultrasound.
We can do, especially in
a low probability patient,
somebody who's not likely
to have a clot, those
patients you can use a D
-dimer testing. D-dimer,
you know, looks at
essentially, you know, clotting
abnormalities in the
blood. If it's, if you have
a low probability patient
and you have a negative
D-dimer, it helps you rule
out, 98% rule out DVT.
If it's not negative,
or if you're not a low
probability patient, you
can't really use the D-dimer,
okay? So D-dimer helps
you rule out. So I could
ask you a question, oh,
a patient came in and
they had a high D-dimer
level of, you know, 2
,000. Does that rule in
clot? No, you can't make any
conclusion. The only
conclusion you can make is
if it's low and you're
low pre-test probability,
then you could say it
helps rule out the clot.
Got that? Very important
concept. Big star on
this slide same thing
star in this slide for
pe diagnostic test the
choice of pulmonary
angiogram the interventional
radiology goes and
they inject the pulmonary
vasculature with dye
amazing best test ever
you see some incredible
pictures let me see here's
a picture and this is a
picture from years ago of
how clear it is um problem
is look at those numbers
on the bottom up to a two
percent mortality and five
percent morbidity that's
crazy that's crazy unless
you You need it unless
you're about to do an
interventional procedure
and you're going to be there
anyway. We almost never
do that. So I could ask
you, again, the reference
gold standard, it's pulmonary
angiography. We don't
do that. What we do, test
of choice, is the CAT
scan of the chest with
IV contrast to rule out
pulmonary embolism, sometimes
called a CT angiogram,
CT angiogram, not a
traditional angiogram.
This is the dynamic. So
you put it in a CAT scan.
that cat skin if you haven't
seen a big open donut you
zip in zip out takes like
two minutes hold your
breath you shoot some dye
it times it to the point of
vascular and you get some
incredible pictures look
at this picture right it's
even better you can see
the vassals are lit up with
contrast that's the bright
and you can see a filling
defect you see those
arrows pointing to clots
so simple uh 90 sensitivity
excuse me sensitivity of
90 especially in the bigger
vascular. Sometimes it misses
some of the tiny stuff.
Sometimes it finds stuff
that's so tiny that has
no clinical impact. You
weren't even looking for it.
But of course, what I love
about the CAT scan too
is it looks at the lung
fields, right? You hear
the lung fields are
blacked out, but you switch
to the lung windows and
you can see pneumonia, lung
cancer, you see everything,
right? So I'm a huge
CAT scan in the lungs,
guys, as you might imagine.
We'll talk more about
that in other lectures.
So,
test of choice for
the legs, for a DVT in
the legs is the lower
extremity Doppler or a
venous ultrasound of
the legs. Test of choice
for PE in the chest
is CT angiogram or CT
of the chest with IV
contrast rule out PE.
Not pulmonary angiogram,
that's the gold standard,
and not a, you know, low
extremity venicogram,
that's a gold standard.
We don't do that, almost
ever you could do mra
but we almost never use
mr in the chest it's not
really the best modality
uh we can do sorry I
lost my spot there there
we go sorry um we can do
vq scanning vq can is a
ventilation perfusion scan
you have a patient breathe in
some uh material you inject
them with dye at the same
time you'd look to see uh
that the areas that have
both air and blood flow if
you have air and no blood
flow you know you have a
an issue there's some sort
of obstruction and that's
what picture shows here if
you look at the picture
on the before side showing
you you don't see a left
lung right you see right lung
no left lung and then you
now you gave them clot
bluster and there's your
left lung so really kind of
cool we do this with patients
who cannot tolerate iv
die um um uh you know if
you have renal failure some
reason not to be able to do
Here's a great algorithm.
If you have somebody
who has a specter
-promembolism, you do a clinical
probability. It's
like a Wells criteria.
Let's start on the
right side. If they're
hemodynamically stable, you're
left side as you're looking
at the screen or the
right side of the screen.
If they're hemodynamically
stable and you have
low or intermediate
probability, you do a D-dimer.
If that's negative and they're
low probability, you're done.
If you have high probability,
you go to CAT scan
and you rule out PE. If
you're unstable, we'll
talk more about that
later, who's critically ill
and who's not. If you're
not critically ill, we
still scan you if you can
make it to the scanner.
But if you're critically
ill, we never send you
to the CAT scanner. We
don't do that. I say, it's
a saying I say, death
begins in the CAT scanner.
We try never to take
a patient and put them
where there's no doctor
and no nurse and no team.
In those patients, you
would do an echo. You would
look at the right side of
the heart and, you know,
approach clinically from
there. We'll talk about that.
All right. So now you're
in the wards. But you're a
third-year student, and you're
drowning, and your patient
is admitted to the hospital
for whatever pneumonia.
And your attorney will
say, how do you keep them
from getting a clot while
they're hospitalized
and lying in the bed?
Well, you prophylax them.
Almost everybody in the
hospital is indicated. Almost
everybody for prophylaxis,
typically chemical
prophylaxis, heparin, sub
-Q heparin called Lovinox.
We also complete what
I call squeezy boots,
intermittent pneumatic
compression devices on their
legs. squeeze, but we know
that's not as effective
as pharmacologic prophylaxis.
It's a quality measure
in hospitals that every
patient is assessed
and appropriately prophylaxed
based on their risk.
In surgery medicine,
again, low-dose
heparin. Typically,
it's low max sub-Q
once a day, and it helps
prevent the clot. It's what
you'd want for yourself or
your family member. Then
there's more specific choices
around the different types
of surgery, but So you
just have to know that
hospitalized patients need to
be assessed and prophylaxed.
Low molecular heparin is
typically the treatment
of choice, not necessarily
heparin itself.
Most side effects less
likely to cause hit and
osteopenia, but it can cause
it because it's heparin.
Typically low venox, but there
is a number of other ones.
What happens if you get
a clot? Then you need to
thin their blood. Okay,
so if you have a clot in
the leg, it's not in the
chest or if it's even in
the chest already, You
don't want any further
propagation of that clot,
and you don't want any more
clots. And the way we do
that is we anticoagulate.
Heparin drip,
full-dose low-moleculate
with heparin, coumanin,
but that's oral. You
have to check level. And
then there's all these
NOACs. That's the novel
oral anticoagulants.
Let's talk about them.
This class of medicine
didn't even exist 10 years
ago, and now almost
all therapy is on this.
They're great drugs.
They immediately
anticoagulate,
and you don't have
to check any levels,
and it's a pill.
Coumanin. And you'll see
Coumadin along the line
because certain diseases
still need Coumadin.
And it's very hard to
regulate Coumadin levels. And
it depends on what you're
eating and it depends on
when you get your blood
tested. And it's a challenge.
But there's drugs,
Zorato, Eliquis, Pradaxa.
The first issue when
these drugs came out is no
antidote to eat
anticoagulant. These people,
when they come in, they
may be bleeding because
the side effect of an
anticoagulant is bleeding,
right? And you have to
educate your patients on that.
But we didn't have an
ant. Now there are.
There's pracs behind an
index, so there's ways
to reverse the anticoagulants
if you need to.
Complications.
What's the biggest complication
of an anticoagulant,
which you're giving
for PE, is bleeding.
Bleeding, bleeding,
bleeding. So put a star next
to that. I could easily
ask you that question.
And of course, the risk
of bleeding increases
with age and duration
and the intensity
of treatment, as you
would think is logical.
Coumadin, you have to
be careful. You have to
bridge with heparin, because
if you don't, you can
get something called
coumadin skin necrosis. We
don't want to never see
it because nobody gives
Coumadin without bridging
with heparin, but it
could, and you certainly
can't use it in pregnancy.
Let's talk about different
types of clots. So now
you have a pulmonary embolism.
How bad is that pulmonary
embolism? You could have
a little one that causes
you some chest pain,
shortness of breath, but, you
know, no big deal with
your antiquity or you're
good. What if you have a
bigger clot that's causing
hemodynamic issues? If it's
causing some right ventricle
dilation or hypokinesis,
or it's causing shock,
hypertension, and even death?
Those two classifications
are what's called submassive
PE, put a star on your
slide, or massive PE.
Submassive PE is defined
as you still have a
good blood pressure, but
your right ventricle's
not working. You put an
echo probe on the chest,
and you say, oh, my ***,
it's barely squeezing.
We've got a submassive
PE here. And I'll tell
you, the treatment
there is controversial.
Massive PE, they come
in, you know they've got
a clot, a big clot, or
a clot causing major
carmines, and they're in
shock. Defined as blood
pressure stock less than
90. They're in shock.
They're not perfusing.
They're going to die.
And we have treatment
for that as well.
Here's an example of what
shows the physiology of that.
You can take a look at
that on your own time. But
so an interesting concept,
that little clot, the guy
with the little clot, he's
a little tachycardia and
tachybnic, we put on the
blood thinner, but it doesn't
lice the clot. It doesn't
make the clot go away. That
goes away on its own, right?
Clots do, they either, they
fibrinoize or they dissolve
or they organize it. It's
going to happen no matter
what. The clot is to prevent
propagation of that. The
blood thinners to prevent
propagation of that clot
or another clot of forming.
So that's a really
important concept. So
now if you come up with
a massive pulmonary
embolism defined as,
like we just saw,
hemodynamic compromise
shock, you need to
immediately Lysed the
clot. And you can do
a clot buster like we
do for stroke, TPA.
Or you can go in, the open
heart surgeon can go in,
open the chest, pull the
clot out. Or now, really
in the past five or seven
years, the interventional
radiologist can go in,
or the interventional
cardiologist, and suck out
that clot percutaneously,
which is really incredible.
It's incredible. And
it's immediate, immediate
that patient is better.
TPA, here's examples of clot
busters, and they convert
to plasmin. They convert
plasminogen to plasmin.
So here's the test
questions. Put a
little star in this.
For most patients
with PE, would you
give a clot buster?
No. And the reason why a
clot buster is, what's the
major side effect of a clot
buster? Bleeding, hemorrhage
into the brain, even
death, all right? So you
have to be dying to need that
level of treatment, right?
Treatment should be
proportional to the disease.
So I could easily say to
your patient has a TPE and
they have some systemic stuff,
but they're not hypotensive,
they're not in shock,
they have some chest pain,
symptoms of breath, would
you give thrombolytics, TPA?
No, no is the
answer. Either the
anticoagulant, they
won't watch them.
For people who are in
shock, conversely, I could
say a patient comes in,
their blood pressure is
60, they're agonal, what
would you do? You would
clot bust them. You
would use a thrombolytic
or one of those other
therapies we talked about.
Surgical thrombectomy
and, you know,
pull it out or
interventional as well.
You can also put in what's
called a greenfield filter.
For some reason, a patient
has a clot and they have
extensive clot burning in
the leg and you're worried
about that leg burden.
And remember, coming up,
normally you would thin their
blood so that clot doesn't
travel. If for whatever
reason you can't put them
on an anticoagulant, you
could put a vena cable
filter in there, which is
a little filter that looks
like a little umbrella,
and it traps the clots in
the legs. It doesn't fix
the clots. If anything, it
becomes a nidus for more
clot, but you can use it.
The problem with those are
they themselves can embolize
and move and shift and
cause all kinds of issues.
So we're very, very specific
on when that's put in
place. High-risk patients
with a big DBT that you
can't anticoagulant. So
that could be the question.
Somebody has a big DVT
burden. You're worried
about it spreading.
You can't give them
anticoagulation because
they had recently had brain
surgery or they had, you
know, they have a GI bleed,
whatever you have, you
can put a filter in.
All right, here's a,
look at that, a clopper
not pulled out of a
chest, right? So that's
a massive, massive,
likely a massive PE.
So here's what you
do if somebody's
hemodynamically unstable.
You can see on the
right side of the graph,
they proceed to
thrombolysis, surgery,
or our embolectomy, if they
are stable, we're going
to look at the right
ventricle and assess what
to do. All right. So that's
a nice pearl for you.
So it's a lot. Let's put
it all together. Virchow's
trial we talked about
that sets you up for clot.
And the clinical risk
factors make you think of
you have to have it in
your differential. You have
to be suspicious as a
doctor of certain diseases.
You need to know the difference
between the diagnostic
test of choice. I know
we talked but there's
a lot of versus the gold
standard. So when you go
into the hospital third,
you don't ask for a
homony angiogram or a low
extremity venogram, ask for
a low extremity Doppler,
you know, ultrasound or
a CT of the chest, you
know, IV rule out the PE.
PE, most of the time is
caused by a TBT. So when
you get looking for PE,
look for DVT and vice versa,
right? Just be really,
really cognizant of that.
Submassive PE, which is right
ventricular
compromise, right? But
no, uh,
uh, hypotension, no
shock. Uh, you have to
figure out what to do with
it. By the way, I won't
ask you the treatment
of us. I promise not
to ask you the treatment
of a cell mass of PE.
Why not? We don't know.
We're not really sure
the right thing. Uh,
it's a lot of clinical
gestalt. What do you think
of when you're looking
at the patient? What's
the benefit of them? Is it
worth it? You have to have
an educated discussion.
It's always about an
educated discussion with
the patient, understanding
risk benefits, alternatives,
and indications for doing
anything. But if you
have a mass of P, you've
got to thrombolyze that
or pull out the clot or
extract it individually.
And I leave you with
this thought. I always,
always, always,
always, always think of
pulmonary amylase.
So thank you so much.
That's my first lecture, you
know, right under
the time limit.
So how do you contact
me? So it's Jason Golbin,
G-O-L-B-I-N, and email
me. My email is It's
lastname, G-O-L-B-I-N,
dot, firstname, Jason, J-A
-S-O-N, at gmail.com.
That's goldbin.jason.gmail
.com, G-O-L-B-I-N, dot,
J-A-S-O-N, at gmail.com.
Email me. I'm pretty
responsive to the emails.
You know, give me 24 hours
or something, but if I
don't get you back in 24
hours, send me a second.
Don't be shy, but I'm pretty
good about it. I'll try
to answer any questions you
have and clarify. usually
not that many on this
one, but on some of the
other ones like around
pulmonary function testing,
sometimes people need some,
you know, further help.
And I hope you enjoyed
it. I look forward to
having four other lectures
with you this year, and
I wish you the best of
luck. Thank you again.